Railway Labor Executives' Association Additional Records 6087
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Railway Labor Executives' Association Additional Records
1944-1967
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Railway Labor Executives' Association (RLEA)
6087
2 cubic feet
2 linear ft.
Records (documents).
This collection contains select general office files from the Railway Labor Executives' Association.
5793327
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Elizabeth Parker, March 07, 2014
EAD encoding:
Elizabeth Parker, December 14, 2017
Biographical / Historical
The Railway Labor Executives' Asscoation (RLEA) was a federation of railroad labor unions, both operating and non-operating, in the United States and Canada. The RLEA was founded in 1926 and dissolved in 1997, with its duties having been taken over by the AFL-CIO Transportation Trades Department. The RLEA's main purpose was to serve as a lobbying group for railroad labor and act in an advisory capacity with regards to rail transport policy in North America.
The RLEA was founded in 1926 in response to the passage of the Railway Labor Act. Prior to 1926, there had been an informal association between the railroad labor organizations so that the various chief executives of the different unions could work together to form a unified course of action that would benefit all of their members. This group became more formalized immediately after the end of WW1. The U.S. railroads had been nationalized as part of the war effort, and the railroad labor organizations wanted them to remain under federal management, both because of increased productivity and because of better labor relations with the industry. The effort was ultimately unsuccessful, and the railroads returned to private industry; however, the railroad labor organizations had realized the need to have a united front to counter the carriers and industry groups and lobbyists.
On May 18, 1926, the chief executives of the railroad labor organization met in Washington D.C., formalized their association with By-Laws, and elected officers to serve the newly created RLEA. The original purpose, codified in the original preamble, was co-operative action to obtain and develop consistent interpretations and utilization of the Railway Labor Act. The RLEA was comprised of the chief executives of the 21 railroad labor unions, including the president of the Railway Employees' Department of the AFL, and each member got one vote, regardless of the size of their union. The organization was voluntary, so no member organization was bound by its decisions. Over the course of its existence, various member organizations withdrew and then re-affiliated with the RLEA.
From 1926 to 1938, the RLEA did not maintain an office, but the amount of work and its importance led the RLEA to open an office in Washington DC and employ a full-time Executive Secretary-Treasurer to run it. The RLEA did not engage in collective bargaining itself, but rather lobbied on behalf of its member organizations, securing such achievements as the Railroad Retirement Act and limiting unemployment for its members during the Great Depression. The RLEA's various areas of interest, such as retirement, safety, legal matters, were broken down into committees, each of which reported back to the executive board on the steps being taken in those areas.
Post WW2, the RLEA played a central role in the Marshall Plan, working with non-Communist labor organizations in Western Europe to establish labor policy and also assist in the work of rebuilding the European railroads. The RLEA was also a major factor in international labor union federations, and its decision to affiliate with the International Transport Workers' Federation (ITWF) and to encourage the ITWF not to join with the Soviet affiliated World Federation of Trade Unions was seen as a major victory for the west.
The RLEA, like its member organizations, did not allow African-American members. As such, it was only representing the interests of white railroad employees; black railroad employees were forced, for the most part, to work without recognized union protection. The exception to this was the Brotherhood of Sleeping Car Porters (BSCP), who in 1948 began a series of successful legal challenges to the jurisdictions over various classes of work. As BSCP's successes in the courts mounted up, and the RLEA's member unions and the RLEA itself were being sued for discriminatory practices, the RLEA finally capitulated in 1950, and accepted the BSCP as a member organization.
In 1950, the RLEA joined with the AFL, CIO, and International Association of Machinists to form the United Labor Policy Committee. This committee oversaw the labor representatives of the Wage Stabilization Board.
In the latter half of the 20th century, the importance of the RLEA declined alongside the decline in the railroad industry itself. As its member unions either merged into single entities or disaffiliated from the RLEA its influence waned, as did the number of its members. The RLEA attempted to counter this decline with the purchase of a railroad at least three different times in the 1970s and 1980s, though they were ultimately unsuccessful in this venture. Ongoing internal battles between the remaining chief executives of the railroad unions further weakened the RLEA until in 1997 it disbanded, handing over its responsibilities to the newly formed AFL-CIO Transportation Trades Department.
Scope and Contents
Inclusive date range: 1944-967
Bulk dates: 1962-1967
This collection is comprised of select records from the executive board of the RLEA. The majority of the records are concerned with the various mergers between railroad carriers that were prevalent in the United States starting in the 1960s. The merger of the Pennsylvania Railroad with the New York Central is the most extensively documented merger, but other mergers between the major carriers are also documented. Of note is the Keyserling Project, a study commissioned by the RLEA to examine the impact railroad mergers would have on both the economy of the nation as a whole, as well as the impact these mergers and subsequent shuttering of facilities would have on local municipalities. The overall thrust of these studies was focused on the job losses of the employees represented by the member unions of the RLEA. The RLEA at this time was also focused on wage rates for railroad employees, and working on plans to stabilize wages and rules for its members. Also of note are the IRS Form 990s filled out by the RLEA for fiscal years 1944 through 1962, each of which lists the member unions currently comprising the RLEA's membership. Additional records found in this collection document the day-to-day work of running the RLEA offices, including insurance policies for employees, general personnel records, and resumes from various applicants.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: /3007: Maurice Neufeld Papers /4055: James O. Morris Office Files /4212: Kheel Center Current Documents Correspondence 5001: American Association for Labor Legislation Records 5001 mf: American Association for Labor Legislation Records on Microfilm 5034: Switchmen's Union of North America Records 5034 MB: Switchmen's Union of North America Memorabilia 5034 P: Switchmen's Union of North America Photographs 5060: U.S. Emergency Board No. 145 Records 5084: Switchmen's Union of North America Additional Records 5139: UTU Records 5141: Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen Records 5149: Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen Records 5182: William J. Doble Papers 5204 mf: Southern Tenant Farmers Union Records on Microfilm 5300: Railway Labor Executives' Association Miscellany 5347: Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employees, ICC, and Erie Lackawanna Briefs Regarding the Railroad Merger 5351: International Association of Machinists vs. S. B. Street Records 5405 mf: Switchmen's Union of North America Constitutions on Microfilm 5478: AFL-CIO Railway Employees' Department Records 5478 mf: AFL-CIO Railway Employees' Department Records on Microfilm 5484: Railway Labor Executives' Association Records 5484 AV: Railway Labor Executives' Association Audio-Visual Material 5487: Vernon H. Jensen Collection of International Longshoremen's Association's and Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen's Materials 5488 A: BRAC Chicago Files 5488 B: BRAC Records 5488 C: BRAC Additional Records 5541: Philip Taft Papers 5552: Railway Labor Executives' Association Additional Records 5583/5: Archives Organization File (AOF) Part 5 5622: UTU New York State Legislative Board Selected Files 5663 mf: Collective Bargaining Agreements on Microfilm 5728: Railway Labor Executives' Association Additional Records 5735: BRAC Additional Records 5833: James A. Paddock Additional Papers 5976 mf: Brotherhood of Sleeping Car Porters Records on Microfilm 5989 mf: Blacks in the Railroad Industry on Microfilm 6030: Archival Collective Bargaining Agreements File 6040 P: Railroad Collection Photographs 6046: Archives Union File (AUF) 6047: Archives Information File 6118 AV: Kheel Center AV Collection
Railroads -- United States -- Employees; Railroads -- Employees -- Labor unions -- United States; Railroads -- Mergers -- United States; Collective bargaining -- Law and legislation -- United States; Collective bargaining -- Railroads -- United States; Railroads -- Employees -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- United States; Keyserling, Leon H. (Leon Hirsch), 1908-1987; Lyon, Arthur E.; Leighty, George E. (George Earle); Beattie, Donald, S.; Harrison, George M. (George McGregor); Railway Labor Executives Association; United States. Railway Labor Act; United States. National Mediation Board
5793327
- Subject File: Railroad mergers, 1960-1962 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Keyserling Project: Railroad Merger Study [folder 1 of 2], 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 2a)
- Keyserling Project: Railroad Merger Study [folder 2 of 2], 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 2b)
- "The Move Towards Railroad Mergers: A Great National Problem" by Leon H. Keyserling, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 2c)
  Scope and Contents
  Published by RLEA; foreword by G. E. Leighty, chairman, RLEA
- Additional Keyserling Project Materials [folder 1 of 3], 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 3a)
  Manuscript Draft
- Additional Keyserling Project Materials [folder 2 of 3], 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 3b)
  Chapter drafts and correspondence
- Additional Keyserling Project Materials [folder 3 of 3], 1962 (Box 1, Folder 3c)
  Press reaction to Keyserling study
- Legislative Representatives, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Passes, Railroad, for RLEA board members, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Personnel Records, General, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  RESTRICTED
- Prospective Employees, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Financial, General, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Statements and Schedules for the General Fund, 1960-1962 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Public Relations Program Advertisements, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  "Exposing the Railroad 'Poverty' Myth" posters, newspaper advertisements, and letters to editors regarding the issue
- Committee to Study Railroad Mergers, Etc. [folder 1 of 2], 1962 (Box 1, Folder 11a)
- Committee to Study Railroad Mergers, Etc. [folder 2 of 2], 1962 (Box 1, Folder 11b)
- Butte, Anaconda and Pacific Railway, Rules Movement, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Job Stabilization Movement on the MKT Railroad, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  (Folder empty of records at time of donation)
- 1961 Wage and Rules Movement, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Radio-Telephone Communications, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- FCC Rules and Regulations Volume 5, with supplements [folder 1 of 2], 1961 (Box 1, Folder 16a)
  February 1961
- FCC Rules and Regulations Volume 5, with supplements [folder 2 of 2], 1961 (Box 1, Folder 16b)
- 1962 Rules Movement (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Travelers Insurance, Group Policy, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Union Shop, General, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Diversification of Railroads, Piggybacking, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Railway Labor Building, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Committees, General, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Safety Committee, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Railroad Labor Participation in 1962 Presidential Conference on Occupational Safety, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Operating Unions, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  BLE, BLF E, ORC B, BRT, and SUNA
- Postage Meter, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- PRR-NYC Merger. Public Relations Committee [folder 1 of 3], 1962 (Box 2, Folder 2a)
  "Committee to Preserve Railroad Service"
- PRR-NYC Merger. Public Relations Committee [folder 2 of 3], 1962 (Box 2, Folder 2b)
- PRR-NYC Merger. Public Relations Committee [folder 3 of 3], 1962 (Box 2, Folder 2c)
- Financial Statements, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Internal Revenue Service, Form 990, 1944-1962 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Tax exempt filing; each year contains a list of the member unions participating in RLEA
- Workmen's Compensation Tax, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Travelers Insurance Company, Group Policy, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Government printing Office, Account No. 11256, receipts, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Wages and Rules, General [folder 1 of 3], 1964 (Box 2, Folder 8a)
- Wages and Rules, General [folder 2 of 3], 1964 (Box 2, Folder 8b)
- Wages and Rules, General [folder 3 of 3], 1964 (Box 2, Folder 8c)
- Legislation. Time Uniformity Bill, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  Time Uniformity Act of 1966
- Legislation. Railroad Carryover of Net Operating Losses, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Legislation. User Charges, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  Highway, waterway and airway user acts
- Legislation. Railway Labor Act, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Legislation. General. [folder 1 of 2], 1967 (Box 2, Folder 13a)
- Legislation. General. [folder 2 of 2], 1967 (Box 2, Folder 13b)
- Legislation. Civil Rights. FEPC., 1967 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  Fair Employment Practice Committee